innogy.com 2017-09-06

# innogy - General data privacy policy

#### General data privacy policy of innogy SE  
version 2.0   
(May 2017)

 **Personal data**

In innogy SE in general, the protection of your personal data is of the utmost concern to us. This is why we conduct our web activities in strict compliance with data privacy and data security laws. Here, we would like to share with you which information we may collect and how we deal with it. We never collect any personal data through our websites without your consent. It is entirely up to you to decide whether you want to let us know this data, for instance when visiting a website, as part of a registration, survey etc.

As part of a registration, contact request or similar you may provide us with your personal data if you agree to do so. Usually, we use your personal data to answer your enquiry, to process your order or to provide you with access to specific information or offers. In this context it may be necessary to transfer your data to another company within the Group. Your data will not be passed on to third parties outside the Group unless your enquiry or the service/product you order explicitly require this to be done. This will be clearly stated at the appropriate point during the process. 

If you wish to do so, you may provide us with additional personal data via applications that are embedded in our platform (e.g. contact forms or services that require a user account to be set up). Different conditions than those outlined in this data privacy policy may apply when using such applications. Should this be the case, we will explicitly inform you about such different conditions in additional data privacy clauses.

As far as individual tasks and services are carried out by carefully selected and assigned (IT) service providers located outside the EU / European Economic Area, a third-country transmission of the data can take place. In addition, a third-country transfer of data may also take place if it is agreed in the contractual relationship with you. In this case, data protection agreements that comply with legal requirements will be concluded to ensure an appropriate level of privacy with the contract partners.

 **Non-personal data**

When you access our websites, information that is not referenced to a particular person will be collected automatically in a log file, for example 

  * your IP address
  * the domain name of the website you came from
  * the websites you visited in our offer 
  * the names of the retrieved files
  * date and time of a retrieval
  * the name of your internet service provider
  * and, possibly, the operating system and browser version you are using.

We and our Group companies use this information exclusively to determine the attractiveness of our websites and to improve their contents. We do not store IP addresses for more than seven days. We store this information for data security reasons, in order to ensure the stability and operational reliability of our system. 

The statistical analysis of anonymised data sets is reserved.

 **Additional use of your personal data**

Moreover, innogy SE will use your data to send you product information by post and for market and opinion research purposes. If you have given innogy SE your consent, you will also receive product information of the type you have given consent for through the selected information channel. You can display and revoke any consent given in the innogy SE web shops under **"My account"** at any time, or opt out by mail or e-mail to 

**innogy SE**  
Postfach 104462  
D-44044 Dortmund  
T +49(0)800-9944009 (free phone number)  
F +49(0)800-9944099 (free phone number)

kundenservice@rwe.de oder smartstore@rwe.de

We will immediately delete any data that we no longer require, provided that no legal stipulations prohibit us from doing so. 

**Specific aspects relating to the use of one of our web shops (innogy SE Energiekaufhaus, innogy SE SmartStore)**

Data entered by you when registering with or ordering from the web shop is collected, processed and used by innogy SE, Opernplatz 1, 45128 Essen, Germany, or by service providers commissioned by the company for web shop registration and use and for processing your orders in accordance with the German Federal Data Protection Act (BDSG). innogy SE and service providers commissioned by the company are entitled to contact you for these purposes (depending on the contact details you have entered this may be done by post, e-mail or phone).

In this instance, registration and usage means collecting, processing and using the data you have entered for the purpose of creating and providing your web shop user account with innogy SE.

Ordering products and services in this context means collecting, processing and using the data you have entered for the purpose of processing your order. This includes usage of this data by and its transfer to commissioned service providers, e.g. for billing purposes and shipping of the goods and possibly making information on a value added service that you have ordered available to the innogy SE SmartHome backend in order to provide this value added service for you.

Your data will also be passed on to a credit reference agency, companies for processing the payment method you have selected and possibly a debt collecting agency, if the transfer of your data is necessary and if innogy SE is entitled to transfer it in accordance with the German Federal Data Protection Act (see also "Specific aspects of the payment methods of direct debit, credit card and PayPal" below).

Should you delete the user account you have created in the associated web shop, your personal data will be deleted accordingly. Your data will be blocked instead of deleted should innogy SE be obliged to keep your personal data in accordance with commercial retention periods or other legal provisions overriding the Federal Data Protection Act (BDSG). In order to delete your user account, please send an email with the subject "Delete user account", stating your user name, surname and first name to kundenservice@rwe.de. It is important that you send exactly the same data you have entered when registering/ordering with us. 

The service providers mentioned in this privacy policy (logistics companies, service providers for on-site installation, service providers for billing and payment activities, telephone customer services and for operating IT, sales partners etc.) will be commissioned by innogy SE in accordance with the Federal Data Protection Act (BDSG) and are bound to the data protection and data security levels of innogy SE. As part of this commitment to data security it has been stipulated, for example, that service providers will only receive data that is required to fulfil a particular order. You may rest assured that innogy SE and the service providers it commissions collect, process and use your data in a strictly confidential manner and do not pass it on to third parties.

 **Specific aspects of the payment methods of direct debit, credit card and PayPal**

For your own safety and ours, we can only approve payments by direct debit after it has been established that you have a good credit rating. For this purpose your data (name, address and date of birth) will be passed on to infoscore Consumer Date GmbH, Rheinstraße 99, 76532 Baden-Baden, Germany. Should direct debit payments not be available to you, you will be made aware of this and other payment methods will be offered to you. 

If you select payment by credit card, innogy SE will pass on the data required for processing your payment to the company responsible for transferring credit card data. Companies of this type are subject to strict data protection requirements (PCI certification). 

If the payment is made via PayPal, all data in relation to your PayPal account that has been set up already, or that is being set up in the process, is collected directly by PayPal. innogy SE then transfers to PayPal only the data that is required to make the payment.

innogy SE reserves the right to pass on your data to a credit rating agency if invoices for correctly provided services and/or supplied products have not been paid, even after reminders have been sent. 

**"Cookie" information that is stored on your computer automatically**

When you visit one of our websites we may store "cookie" information on your computer that we recognise automatically on your next visit. Cookies enable us, for example, to adapt a website to your interests or to store your user name so that you do not need to re-enter it each time you return. If you do not want us to recognise your computer on a return visit to one of our websites, please configure your internet browser in such a way that it will delete cookies from your hard drive, block all cookies or display a warning before a cookie is stored.

 **Using HR-Mobile:** in order for you not having to re-enter your user name when switching between apps in HR Mobile, your registration certificate will be temporarily stored on your computer using cookies. Therefore you need to allow cookies to be stored on your computer in order to register with HR Mobile.

 **Support for and use of the live chat**

On our websites we use the chat service by iAdvize, 2 Ter Quai François Mitterrand, Nantes 44200, France, in order to provide you with additional support when required. In this way we want to increase your satisfaction with our services and optimise our website. iAdvize will only collect, process or store data for the purposes as stipulated by us and it will not pass on the data to third parties, for example to advertising networks, under any circumstances. With this agreement we have full control over our visitors’ data at iAdvize.

Data for the iAdvize service is stored on your computer via the local storage function or in cookies. The data is only stored on iAdvize servers once you initiate communication with one of our advisors. You can control what is stored locally on your computer by using the cookie settings in your browser. 

If you use our support service, the advisor is supplied with information on your visit to our website, standard web data (e.g. browser version and operating system) and also the position of the mouse pointer, so that the advisor will be able to assist you as quickly as possible. The advisor will not have access to sensitive data, such as bank or account information. Please note that in order to achieve the high levels of quality we require from our support team, it might be necessary for the advisor to pass on details from your communication with that advisor to another advisor or to a superior. In order to improve the quality of our support in the future and to optimise our website and our services, the conversations are stored for 3 months. If you object to this, please let your advisor know. The advisor can stop this data being stored at any time.

Please note that the advisor can see your entries as you type, not just after you have completed entering your question/response. You are probably familiar with this function from other chat programs; it enables us to respond to your question more quickly.

 **Information on web analysis**

On this website, data is collected and stored by means of **etracker GmbH** ([www.etracker.com](http://www.etracker.com/)) technology for marketing and optimisation purposes. This data can be used to create user profiles under a pseudonym. Cookies may be used for this purpose. Cookies are small text files stored locally in the cache of the internet browser of website visitors. The cookies enable the internet browser to be recognised on return visits. Without the specific consent of the person concerned, the data collected by means of the etracker technologies is not used to personally identify the visitor to this website, nor will it be linked with personal data about the person behind the pseudonym. It is possible at any time to [opt out](http://www.etracker.de/privacy?et=e8K5Qb) of the collection and storage of this data with immediate effect for the future.

This website uses **Google Analytics** , a web analysis service provided by Google Inc. ("Google"). Google Analytics uses "cookies", which are text files placed on your computer, to help the website analyse how you use the site. The information generated by the cookie about your use of the website will usually be transmitted to and stored by Google on servers in the United States. However, where IP anonymisation is activated on this website, your IP address will be truncated by Google within a member state of the European Union or in other states that signed the Agreement on the European Economic Area first. Only in exceptional cases will the full IP address be transmitted to a Google server in the US and truncated there. On behalf of the operator of this website, Google will use this information for the purpose of evaluating your use of the website, compiling reports on website activity and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage. The IP address transmitted by your browser as part of the Google Analytics activities will not be associated with any other data held by Google. You may refuse the use of cookies by adjusting the relevant settings on your browser; however, please note that if you do so you may not be able to use the full functionality of this website. You can also stop the transfer of cookie-generated data relating to your usage of this website (including your IP address) to Google by downloading and installing the browser plugin under the following link. The current link is http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=de. In light of the discussion on using analysis tools with full IP addresses we would like you to note that this website uses Google Analytics with the **"_anonymizeIp()"** extension and that IP addresses are thus only processed further in a truncated format in order to ensure that they cannot be linked back directly to a particular person.

 **By using this website, you consent to the processing of data about you by Google in the manner and for the purposes set out above.**

The **Google Analytics tracking code** implemented on this website supports display advertising. The **remarketing function** is used for Google Analytics display advertising on this website.

The ads are displayed on the websites by third-party providers including Google. Third-party providers (e.g. Paessler or PRTG), including Google, use cookies. The combined use of first-party cookies (e.g. Google Analytics) and third-party cookies (e.g. DoubleClick cookies) enables us to personalise, adapt and optimise the ads we display on this website based on your previous visits. You can use the [Ads Preferences Manager](https://www.google.com/settings/not-supported?ref=/settings/ads/anonymous) to deactivate Google Analytics for display advertising and adapt ads in the Google Display Network.  
The following Google AdWords functions are used on this website:

  * Remarketing
  * Interest categories
  * Similar target groups
  * Other types of interest-based advertising

We use these **Google AdWords functions** in order to make visitors to this website aware of websites of third-party providers or to address internet users with specific interest profiles, based on their internet usage. We do not gather personal information with our cookies, remarketing lists or other anonymous IDs.

 **Dynamic tracking system**

The dynamic tracking system is intended to identify services from different advertising channels of innogy SE Energiekaufhaus. When visiting innogy SE Energiekaufhaus, data from your browser is collected for statistical analysis. The data is passed on to uppr GmbH, the technical and statistical service provider. No personal user data is passed on in the process. Data collection takes place via a pixel that is embedded on each web shop page. During contact with the tracking servers, common information such as operating system and browser used, the associated advertising medium, the referrer and the IP addressed are stored anonymously. The IP address is used for internal references only and not passed on to third parties. If an order is placed, only anonymous data, e.g. order number, shopping cart and order values are passed on to uppr GmbH so that commission can be allocated to the different advertising partners correctly.

Cookies are used to gather the data. Cookies are small text files that are stored on your computer. It is not possible to track information back to particular persons via cookies. No personal information will be stored either. Cookies cannot damage your computer and do not contain any viruses. You can activate and deactivate cookies in your browser settings.

Pursuant to section 15 of the German Telemedia Act, website visitors have the right to opt out of their anonymised visitor data being stored, preventing their data from being gathered in the future. You can object here: [https://t.uppr.de/tm_optout](https://t.uppr.de/tm_optout.aspx?trackid=B9B925B68A737D56975AB581B427DDB2)

 **General information on online behavioural advertising**

Online behavioural advertising, also known as targeting, enables advertising companies to identify users and assign them to particular target groups when delivering advertisements. This information makes it possible to display ads that are more relevant to the user. 

Behavioural advertising takes place in three stages: data collection via "tracking pixels", storage and processing of log file information and finally using this information when the user returns for retargeting or lookalike retargeting. We would like to explain these steps in a little more detail below.

 **Use of tracking pixels on the website**

Tracking pixels are small images on websites that are used for log file recording and log file analysis for statistical evaluation. When visiting a website, the tracking pixels write information to the cookie file in the user’s browser. 

**Storing log file information in the cookie file**

In order to track your usage, a cookie is stored on your computer when you visit our page. Cookies are small text files that are stored on your computer’s hard drive and that enable the website to recognise your browser upon a return visit but do not allow to identify the user personally. Information about your activities on the websites you visit is gathered (e.g. surfing behaviour, visited sub-pages of the website, clicked advertising banners etc.) All user data is stored under a pseudonym, which makes it impossible to reference the data back to your person and thus to being identified personally.

 **Retargeting und lookalike retargeting**

With the relevant information in the cookie, the user’s browser can be recognised upon a return visit and the user will then be shown ads from external websites that they visited previously. This process is known as retargeting.

In addition, “statistical twins” of the original cookie profiles are identified and targeted based on the cookie information that was cumulated. This process is called lookalike retargeting.

You have the right to opt out of targeting/retargeting. Please use the following links if you wish to do so. Please note: if you delete the cookies, the provider will no longer be able to assert that you have opted out. In that case you will need to opt out again..

 **Behavioural advertising**

On this website, data with usage information (visited websites, number of visits, times of visits, time spent on individual pages etc.) is stored in cookies on the user’s hard drive. These usage profiles are anonymised and analysed using a technical (statistical) process, so that the selection of internet advertisements (e.g. banners) can be based on the interests of the users when they visit other websites later. 

This process is also known as **behavioural targeting**. Under no circumstances are personal data like name, address, e-mail address stored in the cookies in the process. The IP address is transmitted to the service provider, but it is stored and processed there only in a truncated or encrypted format (i.e. replaced by a different sequence of numbers that cannot be referenced back to the original IP address).   
Behavioural targeting is provided by third-party companies that also provide advertising services for websites of other suppliers. These third-party companies then use cookies to compile the above-mentioned user profiles and select relevant data for user-driven advertising via their respective targeting systems. On the websites of the different providers mentioned in this document you can find additional information on data protection policies and on behavioural targeting as provided by those companies.

 **Remintrex** is such an advertising analysis service, used by SmartUp Venture GmbH, Adalbertstrasse 5, 10999 Berlin, Germany, on behalf of cooperation partners. Remintrex is only applied after you have permitted email advertising from a cooperation partner and also explicitly agreed to the use of Remintrex, e.g. when registering for advertising-based services such as portals, competitions or surveys. Remintrex enables the cooperation partner to dispatch advertising emails based on user behaviour on this website.

Remintrex uses cookies which, for example, are placed in advertising-based services such as portals, competitions or surveys by the respective providers of such services after the participants have given their explicit consent to the provider. Via the cookies, pseudonymised information is sent to SmartUp GmbH (the contract data processor of the cooperation partners) to inform them that you (i.e. a pseudonymised user with the ID stored in the cookie) have visited the site, which product you were interested in and whether a contract has been concluded. The information is then stored separately for each cooperation partner on a server of SmartUp GmbH as the contract data processor of the cooperation partner. Using the transmitted information, SmartUp is able to send you advertising e-mails – subject to an advertising agreement for email advertising – on behalf of the cooperation partner based on your usage behaviour and thus your interests.

The information transmitted via the cookies is exclusively used for advertising of products sold on our site.

If you have no further interest in analysis by Remintrex, you can delete the cookie via your browser at any time. You can find instructions on how to this in your browser’s help function or you can opt out directly, using the link provided below.

Due to the pseudonymous or anonymous character of your data we and the aforementioned third-party companies do not require separate consent for behavioural targeting (section 15, paragraph 3, German Telemedia Act). However, you can also opt out of behavioural targeting by the aforementioned companies. Please use the following links if you wish to do so:

 **Targeting system**

| 

 **Links**

| 

 **References**  
  
---|---|---  
  
Performance Advertising GmbH

By clicking the “opt-out” button.  
  
Group M

Please select “Bitte meinen Browser nicht in targ.ad teilnehmen lassen” (Please do not allow my browser to participate in targ.ad) and click “Speichern” (Save).  
  
Quisma GmbH

By clicking the link: “Cookie-Opt-out”.  
  
Xplosion

By clicking the “Deaktivieren” (deactivate) button.  
  
Rocketfuel GmbH

In the “Opt-out” paragraph, by clicking “here”.  
  
Performance Netzwerk* der uppr GmbH

By clicking the link: "Opt-Out jetzt durchführen".  
  
* opt out applies to: Target Performance, Usemax, KUPONA, ad:cmedia, Targeting360, Advanced Store, The Reach Group, Ve Interactive, Vivalu, Kwanko, Adlicious, Belboon, Performance Advertising, Ströer, Kühne & Loos, Criteo  
  
 **Children**

Minors should not transmit any personal data to innogy SE websites without the permission of their parents or guardians. innogy SE recommends to all parents and guardians to instruct their children on how to deal with personal data on the internet in a secure and responsible manner. innogy SE will never knowingly collect personal data from minors or use it in any way or disclose it to third parties.

 **Security**

innogy SE takes precautions to ensure the privacy of your personal data. Your data will be conscientiously protected against loss, destruction, falsification, manipulation and unauthorised access or unauthorised disclosure.

 **Links to external websites**

innogy SE websites contain links to other websites. innogy SE accepts no responsibility for the data privacy strategies or the content of such external websites.

 **Questions and comments**

Should you have any questions or comments concerning the data privacy policy of innogy SE (for example about reviewing and updating your personal data), please contact us under the **heading of “data privacy”** (datenschutz@innogy.com). The continuous development of the internet also impacts our data privacy strategy. Any changes will be announced on this page in a timely manner.
